AI has created this window of
opportunity for consumer app developers
to create these magical experiences that
can hook users and grab their attention
and ideally convert them into trials or
even directly paid subscriptions within
the first session and sometimes even
within the first 30 to 60 seconds.
Hello, I'm your host David Barnard. My
guest today is Phil Carter, an
independent growth advisor and angel
investor focused on helping consumer
subscription companies scale. On the
podcast I talk with Phil about how AI
can turn your onboarding from a chore
into magic.
Hyper-personalized experiences that
drive both retention and revenue and why
your value to noise ratio matters more
than how many features you ship. Hey
Phil, it's nice to have you back on the
podcast today.
Yeah, thanks for having me back. I'm
really excited for this one. So you're
now one of our longer tenured guests.
This will be your third appearance.
I think you're in the top three now of
repeat Sub Club guests and always
excited to have you on cuz you you work
with some of the top apps in the
industry on a daily basis
and have just such great insights and
know how to like condense it into those
like really solid takeaways and
frameworks and and things like that that
I think people really enjoy and and can
really take things from. So
appreciate you coming back on. Yeah,
well it's a real pleasure. Uh thanks for
having me back on again. I remember when
I was first starting my business, I
listened to the Sub Club podcast
religiously as you know, I mentioned
that to you when I was getting started
and I remember hearing Tomas Petrides
and Eric Seufert on the podcast multiple
times and so I'm I'm glad to be among
the ranks of repeat guests at this
point.
So several years ago when you started
your consulting career, you you came up
with this subscription value framework
which you did a keynote at App Growth
Annual a couple years ago. You know, you
published on on Lenny Rachitsky's blog
about it and I think it's really taken
on a life of its own but interestingly
you came up with all of that before AI
really started changing the app
industry. So I wanted to talk through
some of your top lessons that you've
learned over the past few years about
how AI is changing the game for
subscription apps and then of course
it's really helpful to talk through it
in your subscription value loop
framework but to get started let's just
start with that like 90 second maybe 3
minute overview of what is a
subscription value framework so that it
can anchor the rest of our conversation.
Yeah, sure. So I guess the origins
behind the subscription value loop
framework really happened for me when I
was leading the product growth team at
Quizlet and at that point I remember
having lots of conversations in
particular with the VP of product there
who was Nithin Gupta at the time and we
would talk about the difference between
value creation and value capture. And
the rationale was that core product
teams are primarily responsible for
value creation. They're the ones
building new products and new features
and fundamentally creating value for
users which in Quizlet's case was the
students and teachers using the product.
But then value capture depends on a
different team with a different set of
skills and expertise and so that was the
growth product team that I led focus on
things like new user onboarding
optimization and paywall optimization
and figuring out the right pricing and
packaging strategies.
But there was no framework for this and
so I would just talk informally with
Nithin and other members of the product
team and then at some at some point
members of the marketing team and other
parts of the organization about
which team should be responsible for
which parts of this subscription value
loop and what sort of levers we had at
our our disposal to optimize each step
in that loop. And over time I added a
third step which was value delivery
because there was this gap between
core product creating value for users,
growth product monetizing that value and
converting converting it into revenue
and then in the middle you have
marketing or in some cases sales teams
who are distributing the product and its
features to users whether that's through
paid channels like Meta and Google or
through organic channels like word of
mouth and SEO.
And so what that led to once I started
Elemental Growth which is my growth
advising consulting firm was this
subscription value loop framework and so
to sum it all up the subscription value
loop framework posits that every
successful subscription business is
centered around a unique and enduring
core value promise at its core
and then you have three steps around
that core value promise that drives the
success of the business. Value creation,
value delivery and value capture.
And the more effective and efficient a
company gets at optimizing each of those
three steps, the higher your LTV over
CAC ratio gets, the lower your payback
period gets and the faster the company
is able to grow. Such a great way to
think about things. It's funny cuz I
forget if I tweeted it or wrote a blog
post but I was kind of floating around
very similar ideas around the time that
you positioned it and I was like oh
yeah, that's perfect. Like that's
exactly what I've been thinking. Like
you got to create a great product that
users actually care about. You got to
get attention. You got to get in front
of them and then you you got to actually
monetize and so I think those were the
three use words I was using like
attention, monetization and value or
product or something. It's just the the
core of a digital software business is
those three main things. Can you get
attention? Can you create something
really valuable and then will users
actually pay for it and then you know
and then you get into all the how do
they pay for it and how much attention
you can get and the cost of attention
and like all those kind of things. But
it is just such a nice high level way to
think about all these things.
So today we organized your
lessons of the past few years as AI has
been changing things into your top 12
tips and we're going to do four tips
around value creation, four tips around
value delivery and four tips around
value capture and I thought it'd be fun
to just just make it like a we're going
to do an audio listical and it should be
fun to kind of follow along and you can
jump around and we'll probably clip some
of these for YouTube and stuff. But
let's just start with value creation. So
again core to creating a great business
is like you got to actually make a great
product. And then it is fascinating that
AI there are just so many ways that AI
can help you build a better product
whether it's integrating directly in,
speeding up engineering resources, all
those kind of things AI is coming to
play in that value creation. But let's
talk through your top four tips. So
number one, providing a magical first
session. So how does AI help you in that
onboarding which is so critical to
success these days? Yeah, well first
I'll start by saying there's a reason
value creation is the first step in the
loop and that's because without creating
value for your users and subscribers
nothing else really matters and so you
got to start there. Without that nothing
else is going to work. And the first
tip that I have specifically for how AI
is changing value creation is this idea
of creating what I sort of jokingly
refer to as an auto-magical first time
user experience. So what do I mean by
that? What I mean is if you think about
consumer tech
for the last
15 years really since the you know the
first iPhone came out 2007 2008, there
hasn't been that many sea changes in
terms of new consumer technologies that
deliver experiences that consumers have
never seen before. Right? If you think
back to I graduated from college in 2008
and the first time that I used an iPhone
it was like an eye-popping experience
cuz I'd never seen anything like it. The
swipe screen and the app interface it
was just really really compelling. Fast
forward to late 2022
and that's when a lot of people were
using ChatGPT for the first time when it
hit the public mainstream
and it was one of these experiences that
was so mind-blowing that you had I
remember being at a holiday party at the
company I was working for at the time
and all anybody could talk about was
ChatGPT and the CEO gave a speech that
was
heavily influenced by a ChatGPT prompt
that he had put in the night before,
right? And so it was in the zeitgeist
and I think AI has created this window
of opportunity for consumer app
developers to create these magical
experiences that can hook users and grab
their attention and ideally convert them
into trials or even directly paid
subscriptions within the first session
and sometimes even within the first 30
to 60 seconds.
And the reason that's so important is
you guys reported data on this in your
state of subscription app report, right?
You guys first started doing that report
in 2023 and at that point 2023 2024 it
was like 70 to 75% of trial starts were
happening on day zero. That's now over
80% and in some categories it's almost
90%. So it shows that you really have to
convert a user in that first session or
you're not going to convert them at all.
And so one example that people have
pointed to historically of a company
that provides a great first time user
experience is Duolingo, right? Like in
the first minute they're not just asking
you questions about what language you
want to learn and being pedantic about
language learning strategies. They're
just getting you into a language
learning experience that's immersive and
you're earning points and streaks and
badges and it's compelling and it's
gamified and and so that's how they
reinvented the language learning space.
But now there are new AI native
companies and we work with one called
Tolen that's sort of an AI alien
companion
that's sort of your best AI friend
and they've just done such a good job of
in the first minute or two
you know, you have this oracle who asks
you a bunch of questions about yourself
based on your responses to those
questions, you're then matched with a
Tolen that has its own unique
personality and character dimensions
based off of your personality and it
explains the rationale of like why you
were matched with this Tolen and it has
its own sort of character to it and then
you're very quickly put into a
voice-to-voice chat with this AI
creature and its memory and its tone and
its recall is just so compelling it
feels like you're talking to an old
friend. So that's the type of magical
experience I'm talking about that you
can't really experience anywhere else.
And the reason that's important is
that's going to have a a very high
degree of influence on whether or not a
user comes back and keeps using your
product as well as whether they decide
to to pay money for it.
Yeah, and that the Tonal experience is
just such a great example. I mean, it's
like they're using AI on multiple levels
because you are actually talking to an
AI, but what I found so magical about
that experience is that it was the most
fun onboarding I've ever had because it
asked you questions and then it would
tailor the response and and this is
what's so great about AI that you can do
this now in near real time that when a
user says they care about this, then the
response can be, "Oh, yeah, that's
really cool." Or, you know, and can like
make a joke about what they're talking
about or something like that. And I I
forget the exact example, but my
daughter I had my daughter go through
the onboarding of Tonal while we were
driving in the car and I remember
cracking up. Like it was funny because
because they were able to take her
responses and then kind of like in
onboarding you're really trying to
convince a user there's some value, you
know, they've come to the app for some
reason and you're trying to get them
over that bridge of like, "Okay, this is
going to be something I want to use,
something that's worth paying for."
And when when it can be that fun and
that meaningful, it just really creates
a different experience. So, in addition
to like the way Tonal does it, I think
there's so many ways now that and we're
seeing it in the industry apps are able
to do that level like customization and
make onboarding way more dynamic and way
more fun. And not just fun, but useful,
makes it feel like the product's already
doing something for it. If you can
deliver value in the onboarding by like
taking one of their questions and like,
you know, helping solve a problem or
whatever, it's just so powerful and and
the way AI enables that is is
incredible. And it's such a new thing,
you know, three or four years ago
Duolingo was doing a lot of
customization in that onboarding, but it
was, you know, hundreds of engineering
hours and a lot of like set rules and
maybe a little machine learning
sprinkled in and you need a really big
team to do that. And now small teams are
able to do some really cool stuff thanks
to AI and that onboarding is a great
place to be experimenting with it
because of how important it is to nail
that first session.
Yeah, I completely agree. And and one
last note I'll make on this one is in a
world where AI has made it easy for
anybody to write code in an app in a
weekend,
the importance of personality and
standing out from all the copycats has
never been greater. And so, for an app
like Tonal, you can just you can feel
the craftsmanship and the the soul of
the company coming through in those
first 60 seconds in a way that you just
don't see in many consumer or prosumer
software products. And I do think that's
a huge part of why they've been so
successful because they have a very
opinionated product that they've built.
All right, let's move on to number two.
Delivering hyper-personalized
experiences. We kind of already hinted
at this on onboarding, but it's great
because it can go through the entire
product. So, what are some examples
you've seen of of doing that? Yeah, so
when I say hyper-personalized, what I
mean is
if you think about how consumer software
has evolved over the last two decades,
you know, I mentioned the launch of the
iPhone earlier in 2007, 2008. When the
iPhone first came out, it was like you
download an app and everybody got the
exact same experience.
And then maybe 10 years later, 2015,
2017,
there was some degree of
personalization, but you maybe got put
in a bucket. And so, to use health and
fitness as a category, maybe you got
bucketed into somebody who, you know,
was just trying to get off the couch
versus somebody who is already sort of
an an average gym-goer or runner versus
somebody's training for their next
marathon.
Now, with apps like Runna in the running
space or Ladder in the strength training
space,
you're seeing more and more of what I
call hyper-personalization, which is you
got your onboarding quiz. And there are
other reasons to do an onboarding quiz,
which is you get all of this data that
you can use to optimize paid marketing
spend, especially if it's in a web app
flow, but there's this core product
benefit, which is now you deeply
understand this user. And with AI,
you're not just segmenting users into a
few buckets, you can actually create
almost an in-of-one experience for every
individual user based off of their
unique responses to these questions.
That's just the first-time user
experience. And then over time, to stick
with the health and fitness category, as
a user logs more and more runs on Runna
or they log more and more workouts on
Ladder,
the degree of personalization around how
frequently this person should be working
out, how long they should be running on
Runna, or how
how much weight they should be lifting
on Ladder, it's it's adapting
iteratively based off of the feedback
it's getting from each of your workouts.
And so, this concept of
hyper-personalization is another way
that
in an increasingly competitive app
ecosystem, the best apps are distancing
themselves from competitors because when
a user feels like you're speaking
directly to them and your product is
constantly evolving and adapting around
their specific needs,
you know, they they really feel heard
and they're more likely to retain and to
pay for your subscription. Yeah, and it
and it just creates that extra bit of
value. I mean, that that's the whole
thing with Runna. It's such a great
example and what an incredible company.
And in part because they they actually
started pre-AI, you know, before any of
this was possible. And when I first
talked to the Runna team, which I talked
to them super early in their journey, I
was kind of thinking, as I did with
Ladder, like, you know, this is such a
competitive category, there's so many
winners already, Strava's already there,
like what are you going to do? And what
they did was they created a really
valuable, compelling experience. And
even from those early days, they had
those levels of personalization. And
then as AI made it more practical,
they've just gone deeper and deeper on
that. And it just create created such a
valuable product to people. And as you
said with Ladder, you know, being able
to progressively overload and and know
that next right weight, the next right
sets, and things like that, it's just
such a powerful mechanism of value
delivery
to to get that level of personalization
and not just have those buckets of users
where everybody's getting the same kind
of plan, the same experience. So, yeah,
it's just such an incredibly powerful
thing.
Yeah, I completely agree. And and one
other thing I'll say, I had Rick, your
CMO, on my podcast a couple weeks ago,
which was a great conversation. And one
of the themes we talked about was the
niche-ification of consumer apps that's
being driven by AI for two reasons. One,
AI is flooding the app stores with more
apps, which is creating more
competition. So, you sort of have to
niche down as a startup to be
competitive. But two, AI is dramatically
reducing the cost of software
development, which means it's viable to
go after smaller niches that previously
just weren't worth
targeting.
And so, I think Runna and Ladder are two
great examples of apps in the fitness
category, which is one of the most
crowded, competitive categories there
is,
who at least initially focused on
underserved niches to get a foothold. In
Runna's case, it was, "Okay, Strava's
already the dominant app out there for,
you know, people who just want to do
some measure of running and track their
performance. But for people who really
want to train for their next race, for
serious runners who are training for
their next marathon or their next 10K,
we're going to put together a
customized, dynamic plan that adapts to
your running performance over time." And
that's something that Strava wasn't
doing. So, Runna goes and they do that
and they
create a great first-time user
experience and automagical onboarding
flow and they hyper-personalize to their
users, the stuff we've been talking
about. They win this segment and
eventually Strava comes along and buys
them because they unlock this whole new
segment for Strava. Similarly, Ladder
has this whole matrix of
populations of
people who want to get more fit, whether
that's at home or in the gym, whether
it's men, women, and they figured out
how to identify the market size of each
of these different pockets and then
target the right coaches and
personalities to attract the users in
those pockets and then build a product
that hyper-personalizes the experience
around each of those
personas. And so, more and more I do
think there's just this huge
opportunity. It's it's sort of the
classic riches and niches, right? It's
niche down and and find a very tightly
defined early adopter base that you can
get traction with. And then eventually
you can expand beyond that, but it's
always better to start small and and
really focus on one user persona. Yeah,
and I think that's a huge opportunity,
too, that we're going to see really
great companies built over the next
couple of years and probably already
have. I can't think of any off the top
of my head, but like with AI, you can do
so much more personalization, you can go
so much deeper, you can create product
experiences you haven't created before.
So, what's the what's that new
experience that wasn't possible before?
Actually, I just thought of the perfect
example, Calorie AI blew up because they
used machine vision and AI to capture
your calories in a much more
straightforward way.
And is it perfect? No, but is it a great
experience? Yeah. And so, I I think
we're going to see a lot of great
companies built thinking through those
kinds of things. It's like what level of
personalization, how deep can we go
um through AI that just was never
possible before. So, I'd encourage folks
and and then if you're an existing
product that's doing really well, it's
like you need to be think you need to
disrupt yourself and be thinking about
like, what's what's the Calorie AI to my
MyFitnessPal? And you go build that
instead of letting somebody else come
into the market. And then of course,
MyFitnessPal ended up buying Calorie AI.
And so, I think, you know, companies big
and small should be should be be about
all these new unlocks that happen in
value creation uh thanks to AI.
Completely agree. All right, tip number
three under value creation, using
extrinsic triggers to build habits
quickly. What do you mean by that?
Yeah, so what I mean by that is we've
already talked a bit on this podcast
about how competitive the app ecosystem
is getting and a corollary to that is
the average consumer or prosumer is just
getting bombarded with information and
ads and life cycle marketing emails and
push notifications all the time, right?
There's sort of this dystopian future I
can imagine where the average person is
just getting thousands or tens of
thousands of ad impressions every day.
And so
what does that mean? What it means is,
you know, if you're a product competing
for consumer or prosumer attention
as you're starting to build a habit with
a new user, it helps to have an
extrinsic trigger on the user's mobile
device or on their laptop or whatever
device they're using that just reminds
them to use the product. Nir Eyal writes
this book called Hooked where he talks
about the loop that helps build habit
formation among consumers and it starts
with an extrinsic trigger, which could
be an email, a push notification, a
widget, but eventually as the user goes
through enough loops and builds a habit,
it becomes an intrinsic trigger and then
they don't need the reminder anymore
because in their head they just know,
okay, if I want to do my workout, I go
to Ladder or if I want to listen to
music, I go to Spotify.
So
the tip here is
it's not going to work for every
product, but if possible, find a way to
build an extrinsic trigger into
your target users' workflow that reminds
them when they should be using it. So a
couple examples here, they're both more
prosumer versus consumer, but two
products I use every single day now are
Granola,
which is my AI note-taking software and
then WhisperFlow, which is voice-to-text
dictation.
And both of those apps have these very
subtle ways of just reminding you that
it's
time to use their product, right? In
Granola's case, it's linked to your
calendar
and so every time I have a client call
or or some other meeting coming up, I
get a little notification on my desktop
and on my mobile mobile device letting
me know that the meeting's about to
start, which is helpful in its own,
right? Right? So it's not it doesn't
come across as annoying because it's
beneficial to me to know what my next
meeting is and who it's with and when
it's coming.
But then on top of that, it reminds me
to turn on Granola in cases where I want
to be taking AI-powered notes in the
background. And then similarly with
WhisperFlow
so WhisperFlow for those who don't know
is is voice-to-text and so you can press
a button, in my case it's the function
key or the FN key on my MacBook. And if
I press and hold that and then I just
speak into my MacBook Pro, then it will
convert my voice to into text and it
turns out that's a much faster and more
efficient way to write long-form
content, whether it's me writing a
LinkedIn post or a blog post or I'm I'm,
you know, in Claude Code trying to
do research or analysis.
But they have this really little widget
on the bottom of your screen that's very
subtle and non-nondescript. It's not
getting in the way, it's not a
distraction but it just reminds me, oh
yeah, WhisperFlow's there. And so as I
was building at this point, I'm I'm
using voice almost as much as I'm using
typing in order to put my ideas down
digitally.
But when I was first getting started, it
was a very difficult habit to break cuz
talk about 10,000 hours. I mean, the
average knowledge worker is spending
huge amounts of time every single day
typing and so it's it's a habit that
doesn't die easily. But that little
widget just helped helped me get into
the rhythm of like, okay, whenever
possible, I should be using voice cuz
it's going to save me time.
And then this is where I give the
Whisper team so much credit because
they've taken this little widget, which
is this little black sliver at the
bottom of your your laptop and now kind
of like the
Dynamic Island so WhisperFlow has turned
this little black reminder of its
existence into its own island that will
pop up and give you tips and best
practices to sort of extend the amount
of value you're getting out of the
product. And so it's it's just this
really elegantly designed way that they
they're training their users how to use
their product, but then also as they
climb the learning curve, how to get
more and more value out of it. Yeah, and
WhisperFlow also they have a built-in
keyboard. I don't know if you use that,
but I've been using that more and more
and it changes the way the regular
keyboard looks and works because you can
tap really quickly to get into
WhisperFlow, which works so much better
than the than Apple's dictation and so
now I find myself using it a ton and
it's it's right there in my keyboard.
And and so similar to like, you know,
they they do have a live activity
that'll pop up and things like that that
you can do. And I guess it's not really
AI, but it's maybe AI apps using these
kind of features to do extrinsic
reminders, but a great tip to be looking
for these kind of platform features that
you can use effectively to to deliver
those extrinsic
reminders to use the product.
>> And yeah, WhisperFlow is such a
fantastic product and such a fantastic
example. Yeah, definitely. All right,
number four, staying ahead of the curve
with rapid innovation.
Yeah, so this one's sort of like
blindingly obvious,
but I I think
it's sort of like when I when I wrote
the first version of this for Lenny's
newsletter, this was a couple years ago
and I wrote the top 10 tips for growing
consumer subscription apps, tip number
one was build a great product and it's
sort of like, well, duh, like nobody
needs to be told to do that, but if you
don't put that number one, then you're
missing a very important point because
without that, nothing else is going to
matter. I think similarly now with AI,
this has just become so important. Casey
Winters and others have written about
how product market fit is a moving
target. It's not like one line and then
once you cross that line, you're you
permanently have product market fit
because the market is evolving and your
competitors are pushing the bar forward
and so what that means is
with AI, the pace of innovation has
become so fast that if you're not
shipping new products and features every
month and I increasingly every week or
even every day, then you're falling
behind, which means you're going to lose
product market fit relative to your
competition and and very quickly you'll
become obsolete. I think the textbook
case of this recently that everyone's
talking about is is Claude and
specifically Claude Code. I mean, the
pace at which they are shipping new
features and optimizing the performance
of their existing features is absolutely
mind-blowing
in a way that wouldn't have been
possible
pre-AI. But it now is possible and it's
and it's also just it's absolutely
necessary for survival. And then one
other example I'll throw out is
StudyFetch. So this is another company
we've been working with for about a year
now in the edtech space
and they're primarily serving college
students
but they just have lots and lots of
different AI-powered features. So you
can use StudyFetch to record notes in
the classroom similar to what a
professional might use Granola for. You
can use it to
drop in a set of handwritten or digital
notes and convert it into an outline or
have it synthesize
important takeaways to help you study
for an upcoming exam.
You can use it to, let's say you're a
medical school student, right? You can
like upload a diagram and have it
extract the most important terminology
for you to learn as part of, say, a
biology class, right? So there are all
these different use cases
and the advantage of shipping so many
features so rapidly, one is you're
creating a more dynamic core product
experience that can lead to longer-term
user retention and a greater probability
of subscriber conversion
but two
if you
ship in public, which more and more of
these startups are doing, right? So
you're you're constantly letting people
know on TikTok, on Instagram, on Discord
what your new product features are and
and why they matter and you're having
people react to them in real time
it also has a user acquisition benefit
and so this can be a good segue into
value delivery because
it's it's sort of a twofer in that
you're you're improving value creation
while also creating value delivery
opportunities at the same time. Yeah,
before we get to to value delivery
though, I did I did want to stop and say
this speed of innovation can be a trap.
And so I wanted to get your take on how
to avoid it becoming a trap because with
it being so quick and easy to throw a
feature on, it it it's easy to turn an
otherwise great software product into
this like catch-all or, you know, way
too many buttons, too confusing. And
this has been kind of a long-standing
challenge with iPhone apps specifically,
you know, mobile apps specifically. It's
that the screen real estate is so small,
the use cases you're, you know, often
like in line at a grocery store or
whatever and so yes, you can move fast
and build a lot of features, but it can
be a trap if you're not thinking through
carefully how you build those features,
where you put them in in the experience,
how that relates to the rest of the
experience. And for some apps, you know,
creating a second app instead of, you
know, adding more features to the
existing app actually probably does make
sense. So how do you think about
avoiding that speed of innovation as a
trap? I like to think about
the value to noise ratio. So what I mean
by that is I think a lot of
not just consumer products, but tech
products in general fall into this trap
of just maximizing value. And
a fallacy that a lot of companies fall
into is like, well, more products and
more features equals more value and
therefore we should just ship products
and features as fast as we possibly can.
But the reason that's the wrong way to
think about it is the bottleneck is the
capacity of a human brain to absorb the
most valuable parts of your product
experience. And as your product gets
more bloated and complex sure, absolute
value of the product if you just sum the
number of products and features goes up,
but the the amount of noise and
complexity also goes up, which means
your value to noise ratio may
drastically decline. And so, what that
means is as you're adding new products
and features, you need to be constantly
talking to users,
analyzing user engagement rates, the
correlation between feature usage and
long-term retention and subscriber
retention rates to understand what your
hero features are, and then pruning away
the products and features that are no
longer adding any value so that your
value to noise ratio stays as high as
possible. Yeah, that's such a great tip.
All right, well, let's jump into value
delivery. So, your first tip there is to
leverage product-led growth loops to
amplify viral word of mouth and SEO.
Yeah, and so, this is another one that
isn't strictly enabled by AI. You know,
these product-led growth or PLG loops
have existed for a long time, but I
think they've become even more important
in the world of AI because
competition has become so fierce and the
largest paid ad networks like Meta and
Google have gotten so crowded, which
means they're getting more expensive.
And so, what I mean here is
when I say product-led growth loops, I
mean things like personal viral loops
where people are inviting colleagues or
friends or family members to a product
to make their own experience better,
right? So, social networks are great
example of this. The more people who are
on Facebook or Instagram, the more
valuable it is for every individual
user.
There's also social viral loops, which
is
I want to tell people about this new
product whether offline or on a social
network like TikTok or Instagram
to get social credit for being an early
adopter and being in the know. There is
financial viral loops, which is I'm
actually incentivized through dollars
and cents or free subscription credits
or AI credits or some other mechanism to
invite other people to the product and I
get a tangible financial benefit out of
it. And then there's also content-driven
organic loops like SEO or increasingly
AEO, which is answer engine
optimization, that are generated by
content spun off of a product. And so,
an example that I use for this one is
Gamma. Gamma, they just raised their
Series B recently from Andreessen
Horowitz. I think they're at north of a
$2 billion valuation at this point
building AI-powered presentations and
websites.
And
they've grown extremely cost-efficiently
with very little paid user acquisition
because of these PLG loops.
And part of that is they have this
inherent advantage, which is their
product naturally spins off all of these
different presentations and websites
that people are creating using Gamma.
And so, some percentage of those are
going to end up getting shared either
internal to a company or team or at a
conference or a presentation. And so,
there's all sorts of personal and social
viral loop activity happening through
the Gammas that are being created. And
then there's also SEO and AEO
acquisition benefits because as more and
more of these Gammas get indexed by
search engines and are now discoverable
by other users or they start to get
referenced in responses to LLM prompts
on ChatGPT or Claude, then other people
can discover Gamma. And all of that is
free user acquisition that the company
doesn't have to spend money on. Are
there specific ways that you've seen
companies use AI specifically to help do
this better?
So, either, you know, better sharing
screens, more engaged loops, anything
like like Tolen where where that kind of
experience becomes better because you're
using AI. Have you seen anything like
that?
Yeah, I'll give you a few examples. So,
one is going back to value creation,
when you create an automatical product
experience that people have never seen
before, they're naturally more likely to
share. And so, Tolen's a great example
of, okay, I go through the onboarding
flow, I get matched with my Tolen. They
have this great infographic that shows
the Tolen's personality profile and how
it maps to yours. That's a viral
artifact that people are likely to
share. So, that's one example. Second
example is
and we'll talk about this as part of
value capture, more and more AI products
are using hybrid monetization models
where you've got a subscription, but
then you also have to purchase
additional AI credits even on top of
your subscription if you're a power
user.
Well, that leads to an opportunity
around incentivized referral programs.
Where now if I invite a friend or
colleague, I get additional AI credits
that I can use for my own product usage,
but it's a natural hook for me to invite
more people.
And then a third way that AI is directly
impacting these PLG loops is through
content-powered growth. And so, we
talked about search engine optimization,
which is the sort of legacy way of
acquiring users through Google and other
search engines when your content gets
crawled and indexed by those search
engines. Well, now there's an equivalent
with LLM outputs that are increasingly
taking share from search engines like
Google. And so, there are some specific
tactics you can use to optimize your
likelihood of appearing in
a prompt response in ChatGPT or Claude.
One specific example of that, this is
less true now than it was 6 to 12 months
ago, but Reddit overindexes as a source
of
data that these LLMs use for responses.
And so, like one early tactic was go do
gorilla marketing on Reddit in order to
get a following and build a community
there. And then the more your product
shows up in Reddit, the more likely you
are to appear in these LLM results,
which helps drive AEO. Yeah.
Well, that leads perfectly into the next
tip, number two, investing in community
for UGC-driven growth.
Yeah, so, again, this is something that
companies have used long before the
advent of AI or or the mainstream
adoption of AI,
but it's become so important because
people are still trying to figure out
how to use these tools. And I think as
as knowledge workers and and as people
who work in tech, we often overestimate
the degree to which mainstream consumer
populations are fluent in how to use
even ChatGPT or Claude, let alone all of
these longer tail AI products, right?
And so, the example I use here is
Notion. I had Rachel Hepworth, who was
formerly the CMO of Notion on my podcast
when I was first getting it started last
year, and she talked about how crucial
community was for Notion when it was
first getting started because Notion is
an unusually horizontal product
experience, right? Like unlike most
consumer or prosumer tools, it didn't
launch with a single point solution. It
launched as essentially like a wiki
replacement
you know, something like Atlassian. And
so,
as a result, they really relied on
influencers and early adopters who were
creating content on YouTube or other
online platforms to be able to educate
other potential users of Notion. And
then when they became an early adopter
of AI with Notion AI in 2023, they went
back to the same playbook. And they had
these early AI adopters on YouTube, on
TikTok, on Instagram, on Discord just
sort of talking about how they were
using Notion AI,
publishing templates or databases that
they were using, tips and tricks for how
to get the most value out of it. And
that really helped to drive a lot of
organic
adoption of their new AI products, but
it also helped to improve new user
retention because it got more new users
over the activation hump of
understanding how to use the product and
get value out of it. So, they didn't
just churn in the first 24 to 48 hours.
Yeah, I've talked about this before, but
it's almost a good filter when building
products as well is, you know, would
this make a good TikTok video? And so,
if you can build a feature into the app,
and and you got to be careful because
this can be a trap as well as like a
really fun TikTok video doesn't
necessarily mean that it's a great
product feature that delivers value and
stays core to the the app and everything
like that. But it's a fun filter to
think through. I talked to the 11 Labs
team on the podcast a few weeks ago,
and they were talking about how they
write the tweet before they build the
product. And, you know, thinking through
like what are people going to care
about? What's the hook? What's the like
3-second demonstration? And so many of
the the apps that we do see going viral
and doing really well with UGC, it's
because they have those hooks
and can just be such a powerful thing.
Yeah, it's almost like the new version
of the Amazon memo. I never worked at
Amazon, but my understanding is if you
were a PM at Amazon, you needed to write
the launch memo how the product launch
was going to appear you know, in the New
York Times or in some sort of online
publication, but people's attention
spans have gotten so much shorter. So,
now instead of instead of you know, a
news article, it's a tweet. Or or a
TikTok video, yeah. And it is really
helpful to start with the end in mind
because the reality is no matter how
good your product is, if people aren't
willing to give it a shot, it's not
going to matter. It's like a tree falls
in the forest and nobody's there to hear
it, did it really happen? And so, you
you need to you need to start with the
end in mind, which is how are you going
to get your first 100 or first 1,000
users? And part of that is, you know,
writing the tweet up front or
figuring out what the TikTok video needs
to look like up front.
>> Yeah. And to bring it back to AI and and
the theme of this podcast is that these
new experiences that are enabled by AI,
like we talked about with CalAI, like
that was their hook was like, you know,
they show a picture of like, yeah, I'm
tracking my macros, but look how easy it
is. I'm just take a picture and then it
gives me all the the macros for this
this meal and tracks my calories. These
new AI experiences are those like really
fresh things that are more likely to
catch attention and go viral and things
like that. So, yeah, so many ways to do
this these days.
All right, tip number three, using AI
tools to build and test hundreds of
creatives per month. Yeah, and so, this
is probably one of the more standard
tips that I imagine a lot of companies
are already using cuz it's pretty
straightforward, but it's very
important, which is
if you are relying on paid advertising
as one of your channels to grow, and
most subscription apps are, then there
are tools you can use now like 11 Labs
when it comes to voice or like VO3 when
it comes to video that will allow you to
just exponentially increase the number
of creatives you can test in any given
month.
And so, an example that I use here is
Runna. Runna went from, you know, tens
of creative concepts per month to 400
plus creative concepts per month that
their marketing team
is spinning off each month. And when you
think about the implications that has
for the company's growth trajectory,
they're massive. Not just because more
creatives leads to more AB testing leads
to lower CACs because you're figuring
out which creative is working faster and
you're able to optimize and double down
on your best performing ad creatives
through networks like Meta and TikTok,
but it also leads to more rapid learning
cycle, right? You're learning more about
your users and what resonates with them,
which can inform product roadmap
decisions in addition to just paid user
acquisition.
So, this is another example of where you
know, the subscription value loop has
these three discrete steps, value
creation, value delivery, and value
capture, but they're really all
connected as a system and often times
the best teams are finding ways to make
investments in one step that also
positively impacts other steps in the
loop. How do you think about the the
downsides of this flood of creative
though? And and I'll name one specific.
The FTC had a ruling, I think a year
ago, and it applies applies more broadly
than AI, but it's essentially that you
cannot fake user testimonials. So,
technically, if you're creating an AI
video or a slideshow or whatever and
it's and it's like a person, even if
it's a made-up person, and that person
is saying, you know, I used Runa to
crush my 5K, and if it's not a real
person and it's not a real testimonial
in the US, that's technically against
FTC guidelines and you can be fined and
all that. How are you thinking about
navigating the kind of like truthfulness
of it, the preserving the brand? I mean,
yes, you can just spit out hundreds and
hundreds of creatives, but how do you
how do you do that thoughtfully and and
carefully and in ways that won't, you
know, get you fined in the long run?
Yeah, I'm so glad you brought this up.
And again, we can we can do a whole
episode on this, but the the short
version is
there's a difference between
creating
AI-powered ads wholesale through a
platform like VO3 that's handling
everything end-to-end, right? The video,
the music, the the person's voice,
versus
using a real human being, but using
tools like Eleven Labs for voice or Suno
for background music that allow you to
just create
a lot more permutations of the same ad
unit at the same time. And so, what I've
advised my clients is be very, very
careful about going the wholesale AI
route and using a tool like VO3. One,
because these tools are still evolving
and I don't know that they're quite at
the point yet with the where those ads
are fully convincing. Two, because of
the regulatory risk you brought up. And
three, because there are a lot of
consumers who have a really negative
reaction if they detect they are using
an AI ad, which is increasingly hard to
do, but it's a risk, right? Because if
that blows back in your face, it could
it could negatively impact your brand.
But I think the risks are much lower and
the benefits are every bit as high if
you can create real organic content
coming from real human beings, but that
just layers on Eleven Labs technology so
that you can take one spokesperson and
translate their message into 30
different languages using AI, or take
one 30-second ad unit on YouTube or
TikTok and then use Suno to layer in
multiple different background music
tracks and see which one performs best.
To me, that's that's the right place to
be playing in right now. And one of the
better uses, too, for diversification of
creatives is also just using it as a
brainstorming partner. Is that like, you
know, mining your user reviews, mining
feedback you get, mining
anything you can get your hands on,
competitors competitor ads, and then
using that to be able to more quickly
iterate and try new things as well, not
just, like you said, the wholesale
creating assets using AI. Um
All right, tip number four, uh
highlighting AI features to reduce CAC
and unlock new markets.
Yeah, so I mentioned PhotoRoom briefly
on the last tip, but this is one where
PhotoRoom has really shined. I had
Olivier Le Marec on on a podcast episode
last year, and he talked about how
historically, PhotoRoom had really
struggled to penetrate some of these
longer-tail emerging markets. So,
countries like Mexico, Brazil,
Indonesia. And the reason for that was
PhotoRoom, like many consumer apps, is
heavily dependent on paid user
acquisition to scale.
Um but they just didn't have
sufficiently high conversion rates in
those markets in order to get the unit
economics to work through paid
acquisition channels, even though, you
know, the average cost for an impression
on ad networks in these markets tends to
be quite a bit lower than in
markets like the US.
But when they launched their new
AI-powered background feature where you
could like remove a background or
replace a background using AI, not only
did they see subscr- subscriber
conversion rates in the product go up
significantly, but they also found that
by leading with with those AI features
in ad concepts on on Meta and TikTok, um
they got much better performance.
Especially when they put it within the
first 6 seconds of the ad. It just
really caught users' attention. It goes
back to the auto-magical experience,
right? If I'm watching an ad with the
10th version of a calorie tracker or,
you know, or a language learning tool,
it's like, okay, I've seen this before
and I'm like, next. But if I see this
AI-powered background removal feature as
somebody who's interested in photography
that I've never seen before, then I'm
much more likely to click through and
give the product a chance.
And so, not only did this
significantly improve uh their
subscriber CAC numbers and their
subscriber conversion rates, but it also
fundamentally unlocked new international
markets that they previously were unable
to go into at all. We've already talked
a lot about AI unlocking these kind of
features that go viral and that are
really powerful in user-generated
content and stuff like that. And so, it
makes a ton of sense that those same
kind of principles apply to your paid ad
spend as well. And getting that into the
the onboarding and getting it into the
the product in ways that really does um
drive that excitement about the product
and everything. So, let's move on to
value capture, and we've got four tips
under value capture. The first one is
using cheaper, faster LLMs when
performance is good enough. This this is
a I'm going to push back on this one a
little bit. Why do you think that's
okay? Yeah, I welcome a healthy debate
on this one. And and I will admit it's
controversial because at this point,
you know, the best Open AI and Anthropic
models are just so powerful that it can
be easy to just say, well, why would we
try anything else?
But uh Gamma is a great example of a
company that when they were first
getting started, they famously had this
viral tweet in March 2023 uh when they
launched AI-powered presentations that
fundamentally altered the trajectory of
their business. And 6 months later, they
were profitable.
And there are a number of reasons why
they got to profitability so quickly,
but one of them was they were very savvy
in the underlying LLMs they used to
power the early versions of their
AI-powered presentations product.
Which is not to say they weren't ever
using the most powerful models, but in
some cases, what they found was using
some of these longer-tail models, not
only was the performance good enough in
terms of the quality of the output that
they were delivering to their users, but
also the speed of the product was
significantly faster.
And the cost to the business
of the compute power needed to serve
these AI-powered features was
significantly lower, which as a startup
that was,
you know, fighting for its survival in
2020 early 2023, was was really
important. And so, it's just a lesson
that,
you know, at this point, we're all like
waiting with bated breath for the next
release of the hot new Open AI or
Anthropic model. And that's great. Like,
that the frontier of what these models
can do is is so fascinating and
compelling.
But don't forget that there's this long
tail of thousands and thousands of other
models out there, and sometimes those
models tailored to your use case can be
the optimal solution. I wanted to push
back when I saw this one, you know, as
we were prepping for the podcast,
because
I think where you draw the line of what
is a good experience or not is where
this can be a trap. And and we've been
talking about this a lot inside
RevenueCat. We just released this really
cool chatbot where you can talk to your
data at RevenueCat, and and you can ask
it things that you would otherwise, you
know, spend 5 minutes looking up in the
dashboard with all these filters and
stuff. You can ask it things you
couldn't even find in the dashboard
because it can combine things in ways
that the dashboard doesn't currently
enable.
And we are using the like highest-end
models, and we're doing that because we
want the product experience to be the
absolute best it can possibly be. And
we're doing that with the recognition
that over time that should get cheaper.
So, I think you need to be careful not
to over-optimize too soon and figure out
exactly when it makes sense. And I like
the way you put it though. Sometimes you
can create a better experience with a
less powerful model if that model is
tailored to that specific use case. For
for example, I've been tinkering with a
little um
life-coded app that I've been working
on, and I actually think Gemini I and
Gemini Flash specifically is probably
the best experience for that app.
Because Gemini is really great for some
of some things that Open AI and
Anthropic models aren't actually good
at, and it just also happens to be
cheaper. But I think if you're trying to
create the best possible experience and
you're selling it at premium price, and
you're trying to get people excited
about it, you just got to be really
careful not kind of prematurely
optimizing on cost versus just going for
that like best possible experience,
especially in this age where the
competition is so fast where you're
going to have a competitor come out and
copy that feature, but maybe use the
better model and any follow-up thoughts
to push back or echo what I said?
I think it's such a great point and I'm
glad you're pushing on this but I would
I would argue
the the two points don't have to
contradict one another. So what I'm
arguing is
one
the product experience is a function not
just of the output that the LLM provides
but also how fast it provides that
output and how expensive it is to
generate that output. And so if you are
on the leading edge of a prosumer
category where peak performance is the
thing that matters and cost is no object
then absolutely go use the most powerful
OpenAI Anthropic model. But to use your
analogy before if you're CalAI competing
with MyFitnessPal and your target market
is a 20-something young professional who
is not yet at the point where they can
afford the most premium tool on the
market and a faster cheaper model is
good enough then it may very well be
that you're not best served using OpenAI
or Anthropic's latest model. The point
you're making which I think is equally
valid but I think you can reconcile it
with the first point is
all of these models are seeing their
costs decline pretty rapidly and over
time I think there's going to be more
and more commoditization of the models
right like Deep Seek was big whatever it
was a year or two ago because they came
out of nowhere in China and and their
performance was every bit as good at one
point as some of the top OpenAI
Anthropic models and and that has
changed. All that competition is
creating downward pressure on the
pricing of what these models charge for
their API use and so what that means is
you should be thinking about where
things trend over the next 6 12 to 12
months not just the short term. Yeah.
And so I think both can be true.
Consider who your target customer is and
how much speed and affordability matters
relative to pure performance as you
decide which LLM to use but then also
keep in mind that the cost of these LLMs
is going to come down quickly over the
next 6 to 12 months and and factor that
into your calculations. All right. Let's
move on to tip number two offering basic
versus AI-powered subscription tiers.
Yeah so this one's sort of obvious once
you once you break it down but I think
that the key point is it used to be the
marginal cost of serving a user or
subscriber for most consumer or prosumer
subscription apps was close to zero
unless you were a hardware product like
Oura or Whoop or you were say a meal kit
or physical good service like uh Blue
Apron or
um Stitch Fix your your underlying cost
structure was very minimal because
you're just a software business right?
But now with these AI-powered products
and features that's no longer true cuz
you do have the underlying compute costs
to support the AI features and we just
talked about how the cost of LLMs is
coming down pretty rapidly but but it's
still a non-trivial cost structure for
these companies to support and if you're
an early stage startup or especially if
you're a bootstrapped solopreneur who
doesn't have a lot of venture funding
you have to be very conscious of this
and so what you're seeing is more and
more apps Duolingo's a great example are
moving to a two-tier or multiple tier
structure where you have a basic
subscription plan that gives you non-AI
features and maybe a taste of the AI
power of the product but you don't get
fuller unlimited usage and then if you
want the full-blown AI version of the
product then you have to pay for a pro
plan or a max plan or whatever the tier
is called. So you're seeing this with
Duolingo with their Duolingo max product
which is their new immersive language
learning tool that allows you to talk to
Lily and do role plays all all using
voice not just text. Um you're also
seeing it with products like Perplexity
or uh ChatGPT or Claude themselves
um and then there are all sorts of other
examples of tool we've talked about
Eleven Labs we've talked about Tolen
like all these products have multiple
subscription tiers which used to be very
unusual in consumer subscription but
it's becoming a lot more common because
you have to protect against the
underlying costs of supporting AI
features. Yeah. I mean maybe this kind
of reconciles our our last conversation
on prices that you know as as a product
guy I want to just build the best
product possible and and so this is that
opportunity where if the costs are
unreasonable to provide that best
experience maybe you don't just eat the
cost but you create this premium tier
and CalAI would maybe be a good example
of like you know and again I I've
actually said this multiple times I'm
impressed that they were only charging
30 bucks and I actually think that's
part of been part of their success was
that cheaper entry price and it was just
a kind of easy hurdle to get especially
with the the kind of market they were
going after. There's that perfect
opportunity to say hey you know at 30
bucks a year you're getting the 70%
accuracy 80% accuracy or whatever at 100
bucks a year you're getting the 90%
accuracy. So they yeah it is a good
opportunity to still build that maximal
potential product but figuring out how
to tier things and how to message the
tearing I think can be tricky so so it's
definitely something to be careful of
but maybe an option if the costs are
just totally out of bounds and you're
not in a position to be able to to cover
those costs.
Definitely. Yeah definitely. The
companies just have to be more conscious
of their unit economics and their
underlying cost structure. Yeah.
All right. Tip number three limiting
trial lengths and freemium to minimize
AI costs more more more cost-based ideas
here. Yeah. Well and you know as a
business guy who's worked in technology
most of my career it's refreshing
because it's great to have a software
product that essentially has no
underlying costs but that's not the
reality for most businesses and so this
this is just another flavor of um what
we just talked about which is in the
same way that AI-powered features
probably belong in a higher price
subscription tier
trial lengths and freemium product
offerings need to be a little bit more
conservative in a world where giving
away AI features has significant cost
ramifications for the business. And so
Tolen's an example of a company that um
started with a 7-day free trial and has
adjusted its free trial length and its
freemium offering over time.
Um there are plenty of examples of other
companies that are opting for shorter
trials or adjusting their freemium
offering for the same reasons. Um you
guys had in your latest state of
subscription apps report this data point
that called out that despite longer
trials trials as long as 14 to 30 days
often performing better on conversion
the majority of companies are actually
trending in the opposite direction
toward shorter term trials and I suspect
the reason for this if you were to cut
it for AI versus non-AI apps I suspect
this is being driven largely by AI apps
that are shortening their their trials
out of necessity because if you give
away 30 days of free AI feature usage
and you have whales racking up massive
compute costs without paying you a dime
and then they churn then that's that's
not a sustainable business. No not at
all. All right and along those same
lines is tip number four charging for
additional AI credits beyond usage caps
and this is a great way to maybe offer
freemium but make it super limited and
then allow the ability to either upgrade
through subscription and or these credit
systems which we seem more and more apps
using and and one of the things I'll
I'll say too before you dive in is that
I do think consumers there seems to be a
bit of like a consumer reset in how they
understand these cost structures and the
value that's being created. When ChatGPT
is 20 bucks a month I I feel like and
I've I've talked about this on the
podcast recently
there seems to be a little bit of a
reset of like people willing to spend
more and understand that
a lot of value is being created and
almost understanding maybe because they
see the numbers of hundreds of billions
of dollars to these big AI companies
that that like this stuff is just
expensive and so it's like a unique
place we're at in the market where it's
like the alignment of the technology and
consumers is such that I think you can
get away with this in a way that you
couldn't in years past to align those
costs with the actual usage and value
delivered to the user.
Yeah I think that's absolutely right. It
goes back to value creation in a way
right like the idea that a consumer
subscription product could charge $20
per month or in some cases 100 200
dollars a month for max plans
even three years ago would have been
absurd like it would have been rejected
on its face. But these AI tools are
creating so much value that the people
have the means to pay for them are very
willing to shell out that cash because
it it just unlocks so much value. And
then the other thing you called out is I
think it used to be consumer
subscription tools needed to be very
very simple in terms of okay you get
your 7-day free trial and then you've
got a single subscription tier you're
either in or you're out and maybe
there's a monthly plan and an annual
plan but that's it. That's all the
complexity there is. But more and more I
think B2C is taking a playbook from B2B
where for a long time there has been
value or usage-based pricing not just
basic subscription tiers. And so you're
starting to see this crop up in products
like Eleven Labs like Tolen even Claude
and ChatGPT or Gamma where you can buy a
base subscription tier you can buy a pro
subscription tier you can buy a max
subscription tier but then even if
you're on a subscription if you're a
power user who goes well beyond the cap
that your subscription provides you with
you just have to pay additional money
for additional AI credits or going back
to our PLG loops conversation you can
invite more people to the product to get
more AI credits and in a way that's just
that's just another mechanism for
providing value back to the company
because you're bringing in free users
for them. Yeah yeah. It's a great way to
align cost and value and and you know
we've talked about this a ton a hybrid
monetization and and finding ways to
charge more to users who get more value
out of the product and I do feel like AI
has enabled this in a way that it wasn't
possible before and it's kind of
training users too. I mean if you're on
the free ChatGPT you get you run out of
messages and it says you can't use it
again for an hour.
I've actually been frustrated with
Claude specifically when I just run out
and and they don't even prompt me to
like increase my tier which which I did
recently when I when I've been vibe
coding my little app I've been tinkering
with
I ran out of usage and it said it
wouldn't reset for like 6 hours and I
was like well screw that I'm going to
just upgrade so I upgraded but it I had
to like quit the app and like jump
through all these hoops just to get the
upgrade so you got to create a good
experience around this as well but
anyways the point being I think that you
know consumers are kind of recognizing
these kind of limits in the AI age and
so it is more natural to introduce these
kind of things than it has been in the
past and so and especially when costs
can get out of whack it's very important
to be thinking about it and then it's
great that it really is an option now
and not something that consumers will
just instantly bulk at
Yeah well you're certainly not alone
I've done the same thing with Claude
I've I've upgraded my usage multiple
times not just for me but for the rest
of my team and it's the ultimate sign of
product market fit when they don't even
have to prompt you to upgrade or provide
an upgrade flow because they know
they're
they're creating value so fast that they
would rather spend their team resources
just creating more products and features
and value than worrying about their
upsell flow because they know people are
going to upgrade because the product is
so damn good they don't have a choice
Yeah I I do think they should work on
the on it automatically being applied
immediately that's probably hopefully
just a bug that they're fixing I mean
it's crazy you know we talk so much
about product and we have this whole
conversation about being a really great
product and everything like that but
when you're delivering a ton of value
you can get away with stuff
and people will jump through those hoops
so it's kind of an interesting lesson in
this new age of of how much value is
being delivered and then what you can
get away with in in that Totally All
right well let's wrap up with the three
questions I now ask every guest the
first one being what's the biggest win
you've seen in the past year for you you
work with a ton of clients so I'm sure
you've seen a lot of incredible wins but
what would you say is the top win you've
seen in the past year Yeah so one of the
fun things about being a growth advisor
is you just get to work with so many
different companies and and you sort of
start to develop pattern recognition of
what works so there are a lot of
different examples I could point to but
we've been doing a lot of work recently
specifically on helping companies move
from hard paywalls to freemium which
could be challenging it's sort of like
moving from playing checkers to playing
chess cuz it requires a lot more
sophistication but one of the tactics we
found is really helpful there is what we
call a multi-step paywall so basically
moving from a single hard paywall that's
just basically hey you got to pay for
this product now to this product is free
and it will always be free but we want
you to try the best version of it and
we'll give you the best version of it
for a 7-day free trial but after that
we'd love to have you continue paying
for subscription to get maximum value
and so there was a case recently I won't
name the client but we saw a 75%
increase in LTV per user through the
implantation implementation of this
multi-step paywall along with some other
pricing and packaging optimizations
which has pretty fundamentally altered
the full potential size of this business
now they've moved from a hard paywall
that's excluding lots of people to a
freemium model that is is just growing
much more more quickly through organic
acquisition
>> Yeah in in the state of subscription
apps report we we showed that in our
data hard paywalls performed five times
better so I love that your biggest win
is going against the grain and we we
talked about that in the episode Jacob
and I did about the state of
subscriptions is that
there's a lot of reasons to still use
freemium and and don't take that 5x
increase in LTV as a sign you should
absolutely do a hard paywall so it's
great to hear your biggest win is
pushing back against the hard paywall
and opening it up to more people to
create a bigger opportunity
All right what has been your biggest
fail of the year what what fail have you
seen with clients that
especially something you could learn
from
Well I'll stick on the hard paywall
versus freemium theme because it doesn't
work for everyone and so the other side
of this coin is we had another client we
work with where we attempted the the
shift to freemium and the initial
results didn't work at all like we saw
more than a 50% reduction in subscriber
conversion and so we very quickly pulled
off of it after a couple of weeks but we
learned a lot of really valuable
information that I think will inform
what I hope will eventually be a
successful transition to freemium when I
use this checkers versus chess analogy
what I mean is for the vast majority of
apps hard paywall is the right answer it
does convert 5x better and if you're a
bootstrap startup or if you're operating
with limited outside capital it's a much
more reliable and low risk way of
growing your business but if you want to
build a billion dollar or a 10 billion
dollar 100 billion dollar company there
are a lot of examples of of apps like
Spotify Duolingo Strava that have done
that through freemium and it makes sense
cuz you're just going to attract a much
larger user base at the top of the
funnel if you have a free version of
your product Yeah All right last
question growth would be easier if I'm
going to go with growth would be easier
specifically in my world which is
consumer subscription if consumers
weren't so fickle and again that's true
now now more than ever because when the
App Store first launched and and you've
talked about this on your podcast it's
like in a world where there are only 100
or 1,000 apps in the App Store you you
can get discovered very easily and
people will give your product a try for
the simple reason that there's nothing
else out there but we couldn't be
further from that world now you've got
hundreds of thousands of apps across the
Apple and Google App Stores and so what
that means is consumers are constantly
being bombarded with potential
substitutes they may never download your
app in the first place if you don't have
a reason for it to really stand out and
we've talked earlier in this episode
around some tactics that you can use to
help it stand out but then even once
you've converted a user and converted
them into a subscription the odds of
them churning are much higher than if
you were a B2B SaaS business and so this
goes back to why you need to constantly
be innovating and launching new features
and constantly iterating on your
onboarding flow not just to get to
product market fit but to maintain
product market fit and so that's the
hardest part is that consumers are just
very fickle they have short attention
spans they've got tons of other options
if your product is no longer serving
their needs but I also think that's
that's part of why our job is fun as a
as a growth advising firm and it's part
of the reason why we exist is to help
companies navigate that Yeah I've seen a
lot of
tweets recently going both sides of the
consumer market like it feels like in
some ways it's it's the most exciting
time to ever be in consumer but then a
lot of founders talking about just how
challenging consumer is for those
reasons but that's what's so fun about
it is that you know when you build
something that hits when you build
something that resonates the opportunity
is just so massive and then even like
you were saying earlier in these niches
even if the opportunity isn't massive
maybe the monetization opportunity is is
massive that you can be charging 100 200
dollars a year 20 30 bucks a month
because you're delivering so much value
and so yeah it's just such a fun space
to be playing in despite the the
fickleness of consumers I agree I've
never had more fun in my career and I
think it's a great time to be in
consumer tech Yeah all right well as we
wrap up anything you wanted to share
with the audience I just say if you're
working on a consumer subscription app
and we can be helpful you can check out
elemental growth at my website
fillgcarter.com and then I also have my
own podcast called subversive so give it
a listen if you have a chance Awesome
thanks so much Phil it's so much fun
talking today
Thank you David this was a lot of fun
Thanks so much for listening
If you have a minute please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community